[Music]
last time we spoke it was not so long
ago but you've been in the headlights
even more since yes since the release of
the book and and also the beautiful
interview with captain human
yeah well that seemed to start a whole
new Plateau let's say of interest yeah I
thought that yes I've been in the
headlines a lot and a rather unsettling
amount I would say yeah and I don't want
to dwell on the captain human include
too much because you've you've been made
to talk so much about it I think you
probably tired about it but just one
thing that I I think you demonstrated
very clearly about yourself and also
about the saying that patience is a
virtue that you actually in the end you
won out because she stayed calm and you
explained what you actually meant and in
the end she liked words and I think that
actually was an inspiring example to a
lot of people yeah it seems to have been
it although it isn't clear why it was it
isn't still isn't really clear to me why
it became so incredibly widespread I
mean I think the interview itself on
YouTube has something approximating 8
million views but if you add the
commentaries to that lots of people have
cut it up and commented on it I think
it's I suspect it exceeds 20 million and
there was something about the interview
that really attracted a tremendous
amount of attention so it's very
interesting it's it's obviously part and
parcel of the political tension that's
that's odd that seems to underlie
virtually everything right now yeah I
think it's just like
like the intern interview from the
Platonic ideal steaks like this is if
you want you want an interview but
illustrates the cultural world
everything that's wrong about not taking
your opponent seriously and then you can
always show that interview so it's a
great great way to just introduce people
to what's wrong with the political
discourse I think I have I have a
hypothesis to run by you yes well so
imagine what's happening is this the
we're in the midst of a technological
transformation and the online video
services are displacing network and
cable television and the online print
services are displacing the traditional
print media so let's say that okay so
there's increasing desperation on the
part of the traditional media and so
then let's say that as a consequence of
that that I did that additional
nervousness and instability first of all
many people are leaving second budgets
are being cut and third there's
increasing desperation for to hold on to
market share and as a consequence of
that more and more articles are
polarized because they attract more
attention and that that's driving the
political polarization in part does that
seem reasonable to you yes I do think
that seems reasonable and I do think you
also have a great need for the
established media to debunk sort of the
the people who are popular on YouTube or
have podcasts and are free free from the
the big media houses and the TV channels
so you think it's also direct
competition yes but I'm not sure if it's
sort of a conscious effort I think also
it's incompetent sometimes you know it's
never never
everything together like all bright
lights extremism populism and they have
a very hard time discerning what's what
and the real Nazis from just people
having legitimate ideas and the
legitimate
yeah well that that's another issue
right is that it's in the radical left's
interest to lump everyone who opposes
their their ideological attempts into a
single terrifying category because if if
they had to contend with the fact that
you can be reasonable centrist or even a
reasonable Center leftist and dispute
the validity of identity politics as a
framework for conducting a political
discussion if you have to accept that
reasonable people can do that then you
have to accept that reasonable people
can object your ideology and that
implies that your ideology isn't
reasonable so there's every reason for
people on the radical left to not only
assume that their opponents are
reprehensible but to make the case that
they're reprehensible without ever
bothering to scratch below the surface
so I think that's happening too and then
of course I never want to let the
universities off the hook and I think
the fact that the universities have
allowed and encouraged the growth of
reticle left ideology and the humanities
and the social sciences is absolutely
completely inexcusable so I might even
prove fatal to the universities we'll
see about that
but it wouldn't surprise me universities
have been around a long time though the
last we spoke I was doing a piece on how
radical feminism had been mandatory for
a course long university and we spoke
about that the
was mandated to include you you get
Butler in this course and I continued
writing about the universities and it
goes much deeper in swinging it goes
even white if you look at the grants if
you look at its we have ten ten billion
crona's which are being distributed from
the state and they are they have the
gender mainstreaming that's is taking
place in the you know universities when
it comes to courses and the reading
lists and the professors is also when it
comes to the grants so you have to
include a gender perspective or at least
you have to specify why you don't have a
gender perspective right which is
probably fatal yeah exactly
so one of my friend of mine that I got
to know him via his dog because I have a
dog and so our dogs became friends and
then we became friends so he made his
giddy about Travis wild and wine
droughts and and how do you say
domesticated plants no gap yeah yeah so
the difference in behavior sounds very
boring but it's actually kind of
interesting one thing but he was about
to not get his not getting grant because
he didn't think you know gender
perspective yep and so well I know now
that and that's it ten years ago and now
it's it's spreading so I'm getting a lot
of stories about that so it's crazy the
universities are really it's shifted
into second gear here in Sweden at least
yeah it's the same it's it's happening
everywhere in the West I would say our
government just handed down a budget and
every as far as I can tell from the
initial response and every government
program has to include a gender
perspective now in the same manner and
so our government is deciding to solve a
problem that doesn't exist well what's
happened is that we've accepted
hoody we've accepted equality of outcome
as the measure by which we're going to
judge the fairness of organization's
operations at the same time when the
social science research is stacking up
on the other side of the distribution to
state ever more clearly and with ever
more with ever less doubt that as you as
you flatten out the sociological
landscape so that men and women are
treated more equally that the difference
in their occupational choices widens
it's become crystal clear and the the
response to that from the radicals is
that pseudoscience even though the
people who are doing these studies
aren't conservative there aren't
conservatives in the social sciences and
so people do these studies and they're
shocked by the results they publish them
because they're good scientists not
because these findings buttress their
ideological position and Plus whose
ideological position wasn't to wish that
as you flatten out the sociological and
political landscape you make men and
women more different who is hoping for
that no one was hoping for that so as
the science stacks up the legislative
and political attempts to silence it and
to mount an ideological counter-attack
multiplied yeah and we need more we need
more more general science now because
the differences are accelerating so no
need even more yeah more of the same but
I would like to jump into the to the
book and see what because I read your
book and or I didn't really read it I
actually listened to it which was I can
really recommend to people because you
know you did a fantastic job of reading
the book by yourself and
so thank money I was looking at the
reviews on audible and there's a
performance review and a content review
yeah the performance review is higher
than the content review it
what what to think about that I don't
know whether I should be happy about
that or not happy about that it's not
much difference but I thought it was
comical I think you should stop writing
and you should just be a narrator of
books I think that's the takeaway well
I'm going to do an audio book version of
maps of meaning oh really yes that's
great
yes so that's coming and that that'll be
like 25 hours long or something like
that probably more so yeah that's the
first book I read as an as an audiobook
was better angels of our nature by
Steven Pinker hmm it's like 50 hours or
something so it was a 25 hours it's not
so bad I think maybe I'm out too because
it's a longer book I'm probably I'm
probably under estimating the amount of
time we'll sit but the rule the rules in
your book yeah I think the first rule
stand up straight with his shoulders
back I think that's really when you read
the chapter it's it's really good
chapter but I as last time when I was
about to speak to you I I went into the
Urim Pearson fan groups in Sweden and I
asked them what what do you think I
should ask you or him and then one of
the guys was sir he said I really like
the book but when he says stand up
straight with your shoulders back
I think he should explain more how to do
it and then a lot of the helpful other
guys in the thread started giving him
physical exercises how to strengthen the
muscles between the shoulder dress it
was like a long thread on how to how to
build your chest up like and then in the
end like after 20 or 30 comments like
somebody suggests that maybe maybe
you're done didn't mean it literally he
also meant it figuratively
so but it was no no no meanness or
anything but then yeah it wasn't it
wasn't the physical advice it was so
mostly a sort of a psychological advice
so yeah well it's a good place where the
metaphorical and the literal meet yeah
well and the important part
that chapter I think apart is that I was
really trying to make a case and this is
a case that needs to be made over and
over and over until people understand it
there's a book I would recommend that
was recently written called the great
leveller Walter Shaw Dell and it's a
study of inequality and it's a brutal
book because one of the things she Adele
does is he calculates inequality
coefficients like the Gini coefficient
which is a measure of inequality
economic inequality and he looks over
the empirical data to see if there's any
relationship between the the left or the
right wing nature of a government and
the inequality in the society and so
what you'd hope because inequality is
actually a genuine problem you'd hope
that left-wing governments were better
at regulating inequality than right-wing
governments you'd hope that there's no
evidence for that whatsoever so I'm
making a case in Chapter 1 that
hierarchies exist and because
hierarchies exist inequality exists or
at least the two things are are
indistinguishable at many levels but
that you can't blame the existence of
hierarchy or inequality on something
proximal like capitalism or Western
society inequality is the rule all the
way back down to crustaceans and so when
the Marxists complain about inequality
and how intractable it is well they have
a point but when they blame it on
capitalism they're not taking the
problem seriously it's way worse than
the Marxist think because inequality is
genuinely a problem now the yeah but
it's a problem in in in a bunch of ways
the first is is that those at the top
tend to get more and those at the bottom
tend to end up with zero and zero is
really not good now you might say well
in a capitalist society in a modern
industrial capitalist society people
tend not to end up at zero so much and
that seems to be true it is definitely
the case and and I think Pinker has done
a good job of outlining this the people
at human progress org are doing a good
job of the two
it's definitely the case that our modern
societies are making the poor much less
absolutely poor so we've we've decreased
poverty worldwide between 2000 and 2012
by 50% a massive accomplishment we
should be partying in the streets about
it
it's an amazing accomplishment but
inequality is still a problem so so that
chapters about how deep the problem is
now the suggestion is is that to compete
in a world where there's unequal outcome
your best bet is to take the full
tragedy of being full-frontal
essentially right to open yourself up to
the catastrophe of existence and to move
forward with courage and and and with
nobility and with with truth on your
tongue
that's your best bet and I do believe
that now I can give you an example of
that we did research on a program called
the Future authoring program and it's a
part of the suite that's offered at self
authoring calm and we did the research
the idea was to produce psychological
interventions that were very cost
effective that could be distributed to
many people but we wanted to test them
because you never know if you're idiots
intervention is gonna do something good
or something bad
that's like rule number one for a
serious social scientists assume your
idiot intervention will either be
useless or harmful because those are the
most likely outcomes right and any
social scientist who's truly credible
understands that those who don't are not
educated properly so anyways we tested
the future authoring program and we
mostly tested it in Holland and we did
some stratification by group so in
Holland this was at the Rotterdam school
of at the Rotterdam School of Management
and Erasmus University we had thousands
of University students do the future
authoring program where they laid out a
plan for their life
and they tried to optimize their lives
along they wanted to consider their
friendships intimate relationships
career choices educational choices
mental and physical health use of drugs
and alcohol and use of time productively
outside of work to optimize across all
those levels and then to avoid
catastrophic pitfalls so you write about
what your life could be like if you
could have what you needed in three to
five years and then what write about
what your life could be like if
everything fell apart on you and and
things went bad all right
so they all did this exercise now before
the exercise the Dutch women were
outperforming the Dutch men let's say
the Caucasians and the non-western
ethnic minority women were doing worse
than the Dutch men and the non-western
ethnic minority men were doing worse the
worst of all four groups about an eighty
five percent performance decrement
compared to the Dutch women two years
after the intervention they were doing
better than the Dutch women right man it
blew us away we couldn't believe and
that's research published with Michaela
shipper and and and some other
colleagues at from Holland and what was
so interesting about that was that a
psychological intervention seemed to
remove the barriers that were produced
by what was hypothetically a
sociological barrier it might be that if
you're you know an immigrant to a
country that you don't have your story
straight because it's so complicated
you know so you need a better plan
so and that's part of standing up it's
like okay man make a plan for the future
plan a good future and and move forward
towards it and also one one thing that I
took away from it was from the chapters
and take yourself seriously otherwise no
one else will yeah if you don't stand up
for yourself you will get pushed down
and pushed over and not be taking notice
oh yeah yeah well I think the way you
take yourself seriously is you you start
to construe yourself as a player in the
catastrophe of the world know the world
and this is a motif route 12 rules for
life in many ways
is a very dark book although it has a
very optimistic central message the
darkness is life is tragic and tainted
by malevolence but the optimism is
there's a hell of a lot more to you than
you think
and I don't think that's a message
that's really good for people because
everyone knows that life is a
catastrophe that's stated by malevolence
everyone knows that even if people don't
want to admit it at the bottom of their
heart they know it and I think they also
suspect that there's more to them than
meets the eye so and and so so the the
trick to taking yourself seriously is to
understand that your errors count they
make things worse like it really is the
case that it matters whether you get
your act together at least because if
you're fragmented and disillusioned and
resentful and angry and working to make
things worse you really can make them
worse the school shooters are a good
example of that people who become so
nihilistic and and desperate and then
angry that you know they they they
slaughter the innocent in in a in a fit
of vengefulness like that's third of the
bottom and of of the descent for human
beings it's really terrible you get the
sense I'm gonna divide this question
because the you you you you deal a lot
with Christianity and Christian thought
both mostly with the Old Testament but
also with the New Testament and the
Christian motifs and but you get the
sense from from your book that and from
your teachings and when we talk about
this that we can really create hell for
ourselves in this world and we have no
problem with creating a variety of
health for ourselves and for others so
that's within our grasp in our grasp you
bet
that's exactly right is that hell is
definitely within our grasp yeah
and and I think with our ingenuity we
can invent many kinds of health but I
would also do you think there's a do we
have the capacity to create paradise on
earth do you think is that within their
grasp I think that that's what we
struggle upwards toward you know I was
thinking recently about this this image
came to mind of st. Joseph's oratorio in
Montreal which is a huge religious
building it's one of the biggest
Cathedral I don't think it's a cathedral
because I think it's an oratorio
although I don't know technically the
difference but it's one of the biggest
religious edifices in the world and it
was built in the latter half of the 20th
century which is quite interesting
because most buildings of religious
significance weren't built that late but
anyways it's up on Mount Royal so it's
up on the hill and so it's the city on
the hill right it's the Universal City
on the hill it's an image of perfection
it's its lattice like stonework lit like
the interior of a forest devoted towards
the glory of being in God so it's an
image of paradise we could say and then
it's at the top of a hill and you climb
up to it as a consequence of a very
large staircase set into the hill and
pilgrims went there quite regularly in
the 20th century who were often
physically disabled and so they would
struggle up the hill on their crutches
or or or or with their with their with
their damaged limbs and with their
illnesses and so they would struggle up
the hill towards the heavenly City
essentially and that's what were to do
that's correct that's it's a drama that
when people were acting out now
st. Joseph's also happens to be full of
crutches that people left there for
which is quite interesting to see but
but that doesn't that doesn't matter in
some sense so much as the symbolic
meaning is all these damaged people who
were carrying a terrible load like they
weren't just subject to the normative
tragedy of being they were also
physically disabled would go there and
struggle up these hundreds of stairs as
they were trying to ask sand instead of
descending and it's like well we
certainly believe in hell if we have any
sense if you don't believe that human
beings can create hell then you're a
child you're a naive child you know
nothing you know nothing about history
or yourself and you say well can we can
we bring paradise into being well no but
maybe we can at least walk up the hill
away from hell and who knows what we
could do if we took it seriously if we
took our the idea that we needed to
shoulder our burden nobly and with truth
if we took that seriously as serious as
the hell should make you take it who
knows what we could accomplish you know
as I said we've lifted you've reduced
the poverty rate in the world by 50%
from the year 2000 to the year 2012 and
something like 300,000 people are being
attached to the power grid now worldwide
I don't remember if it's a week or a day
but it's either of those metrics is
still pretty good your fastest growing
economies are in Africa like you know
we've made amazing strides in the last
50 years and they seem to be
accelerating and so I don't know what
the upper limit for us is if we don't
dissolve ourselves into idiot identity
politics and and and start a civil war
no yeah so I think one of the the
reasons why we have very I certainly do
but I think people in general do as well
I have a very easy time imagining
horrible horrible things and and
daydreaming about horrible things
horrible things that can happen to you
horrible things that you could do and
and but it's very hard to imagine heaven
for example yeah you get Dante's Inferno
it's I think he wrote about heaven as
well I'm not yes that's a really boring
book like angels angels sing' White's
dresses singing and stuff like that and
it's it doesn't sound like heaven to me
it's a hell sounds like hell
right have a nice night for real it's
interesting because you know I would say
mainstream
Christian's especially on the Protestant
end have tried to force hell out of the
human imagination over the last hundred
years and maybe as a way of making
Christianity more marketable although I
don't think it's worked but I do think
that belief in hell metaphorically let's
say although I tell you if you're in one
of those situations it feels eternal so
that's something to keep in mind too but
I think it's unbelievably salutary
because even though we can't imagine
heaven so clearly we can certainly say
well at least it's not our switz right
yeah I'll agree on that whatever it is
it's as far away from our wits as you
can get yeah and that's that's a
direction you know it's it's it's not as
specific as you might like it to be but
that's also why I've been suggesting to
people that they think about this
locally it's like okay we're not so sure
what the Utopia might be and we know
that collectively presuming a utopia
also seems to be a dangerous thing but
there are stupid things that you're
doing to make your life and the life of
people around you more wretched and
miserable than necessary and it's
hypothetically the case that you could
stop doing some of them so there's a
good place to start it's nice and humble
it's like you're less than you could be
and you know it and there's things you
could do about that and you know it so
so maybe maybe it would be okay to take
a step in the right direction I think
you you say in the book and you often
return to that basic truth and and you
say that you you you arrive at this when
you contemplate the horribleness of the
20th century with all suites and the
Gulag and that life there is life is
suffering and and you can you can
produce away the pain of existence and
there's no totalitarian that can reduce
away that you could just forget it you
know in Venezuela now it's illegal to
less list the the cause of the death of
a child as starvation in the hospitals
oh that's convenient
oh yes isn't that something isn't
something so there we go now we've got
the Utopia it's now illegal to die of
starvation in a hospital in Venezuela or
at least to have it listed and that's
exactly it man there's a little slice of
hell for you yeah but I I would say that
one of the it's easier to move away from
it's not easy but it's it's easier to
stop doing causing harm and causing
suffering than to arrive at bliss that's
sort of a basic way we are very bad at
people are pretty bad at having eternal
bliss in this life yeah well yeah it's
not easy to conceptualize what it would
be I mean you do see you do taste it at
times you know you taste it with music
and of course that's why there's imagery
of angels and and and the heavenly hosts
singing you know because people do get a
taste of what paradise might be like
when they listen to music which is why
music is so powerful for people because
it speaks of a kind of transcendent
harmony of the of the layers of being
and it engages a person in that and you
get that as well when you're engaged in
what you're doing and deeply engaged
what you're doing and finding meaningful
but I mean stepping rapidly away from
hell might be a form of bliss you know
to know that at minimum you're not
contributing to the terrible suffering
of the world and maybe you're doing
something to to lift the to lift the
burden in a positive way I mean it's
really complicated because you don't
want everything to be easy that's not a
good idea for utopia
everything's blissful and easy and all
you're doing is laying back and eating
peeled grapes you know it's if there's
nothing to that that would last more
than a week you need and you need an
adventure and you need a struggle but
perhaps we could have the adventure and
the struggle without the pointless
suffering and malevolence we could at
least aim at that and then and who knows
what we might transmute that into at
least we might be able to transmute it
into lives that are meaningful despite
their suffering that would be a good
start and I do believe that that's a I
believe that that's an attainable
realistic
I believe that that we are strong enough
as in our essence to rise above the
tragedy of existence and to live nobly
and with purpose and honorably I believe
we can do that and so that's why I think
12 rules for life is a fundamentally
optimistic book because I also think
that that's a believable message no
one's going to say well believe that
well we're going to eradicate suffering
and and malevolence it's like that no I
don't think so but we can constrain it
within the confines of our own being hmm
and that's good enough that's a good
start about in Chapter rule number eight
you say tell the truth that's that's
rule number eight if you tell truth Abby
stop life and you write that it is our
responsibilities to see what is before
our eyes courageously and to learn from
it even if it seems horrible even if the
horror of seeing it damages our
consciousness and half biases and then I
just thought about that for a while and
and I reflected about during the when
Isis invaded Iraq in 2014 I think it was
for 2015 2014 was and I was one of the
few who wrote about what was following
that right then because nobody thought
it would take over such a large part of
Iraq and then I was watching loads of
videos of mass killings and
decapitations and murders and I was
seeing I had contact with eyewitnesses
we are journalists whose name is nur
aquino and it was horrible really really
horrible most the most horrible things
I've ever seen and because I had contact
with nur akeno's
had family members down there Assyrians
Christians were being murdered and
driven from the homes and this was even
before singe or were they took this sick
snakes there and they murdered
whole people you see this yeah yeah so
it was really horrible episode for them
I mean of course that's the big deal but
III felt I had a responsibility to to
see this series for myself yet not just
listen to journalists who hadn't seen it
because I was writing about it a lot
myself and I could feel it changing me
yeah this is the the absolute as close
to absolute darkness as I have ever come
home because it was it was it was not
historical these four people some
younger than me some older but they were
it was happening as I was watching it
and then I thought about the quote by
Nietzsche if you gaze into the abyss the
abyss also gazes into you I really felt
that thinking about this one when I read
your work and I thought that I would ask
you that how how can you be certain that
you can defeat the darkness that when
you face that I mean it sir I don't
think that you can be certain that you
can you say well if you go to face the
dragon to get the gold it wouldn't be a
dragon if it couldn't eat you the issue
isn't that there is the issue isn't that
you're certain of success the issue is
that you don't have a better pathway and
so if you're going to confront the
dragon of chaos say and dare to attain
the goal then you have to put yourself
on the line for it but paradoxically it
seems the more you're willing to put
yourself on the line for it the higher
the probability of your success which is
also the part of opening yourself up to
the catastrophe no in that's that's why
Christianity has increasingly occupied
the theater of in my imagination because
there's this idea that you know little
even speaking psychologically that
whatever Christ represents whatever that
image is it is in part the call to
accept the catastrophe of existence to
accept it voluntarily
because the fundamental story is that
Christ went to his torturous betrayal
with his eyes open right and well that's
a hell of a thing it's no wonder that
images never left people's imagination
because that's there isn't you can't ask
any more of someone than that
and you might say well is it okay that
everything will be asked of us and the
answer is it doesn't matter because
everything is going to be asked of you
like you're going to die you're going to
have to accept that in one in one form
or another the question is how well the
answer is well you have to open your
arms you have to accept it you know and
there's an idea in the New Testament
that if you can if you can love fate
deeply enough you can trance you can
transcend your the limitations of your
mortality it's something like that and
you know that's that strikes me as a
plausible possibility now you said when
you were watching all those things that
that changed you yeah you mean what did
it what did it change you realize at
least I did what you're facing is
something real and if if evil has has
meaning if there is evil that that is
evil and what if that was sort of and
then you have a terrorist attack in
Sweden and you store the story things
like what would I what would I do if I
were in that situation and you speak to
people who have who have relatives there
and you realize that you're very lucky
that you're living in Sweden and not
there because I I think it would not be
very hard to take up arms against these
people well that's that's the thing is
that you realize you realize things
about yourself if you gaze into that of
this well you know the terrible thing
too is and this is a motif again that
also runs through 12 rules for life is
that well let's say when the
when the I'll give you a personal
example so when I heard about what
happened in Cologne on the new on New
Year's Eve and I see I had a situation
where my son was mugged a number of
years ago and he was mugged by a gang of
kids that were brought into our
neighborhood as a favor to them so that
they could play basketball in a local
Boys and Girls Club and there was about
six or seven of them 18 years old and
they mugged my 13 year old son and took
his his I think he'd they took his cell
phone and he came home and he was shaken
up mostly with anger because he couldn't
believe that six 18 year old young men
could be so cowardly that they would
gang up on a 13 year old kid like so for
him it was a betrayal of humanity
apart from being afraid but mostly it
was anger on his part and I was
absolutely outraged so I contacted the
police and I contacted the nearby club
that had sponsored the kids and I said
look this is what happened and they did
nothing about it the club knew who it
was and wouldn't release the names
because of confidentiality and all sorts
of other nonsense and I had this fantasy
that went on for weeks about standing
outside the Boys and Girls Club and
waiting for those kids with a lead pipe
because I was not happy but you know I
was and I couldn't pursue it with any
degree of legal I couldn't pursue it to
the degree that I wanted to in the legal
framework because at the same time my
daughter was very ill and that was
taking precedence but you know I had
these terrible fantasies come up over
and over they very very dark fantasies
and you know I talked it over with my
son because I told him what was
happening in my imagination because I
wanted to let him know that this really
bothered me that he was attacked and
that I wasn't going to put up with it
but I also understood that that's not
seats I would have been I think I would
have been a very weak man to not have
had those feelings and then you think
well lots of times it's the better man
that takes up arms but it isn't
necessarily the best man who takes up
arms because maybe there's a
place past that you might say well it's
naivety and cowardice that stops you
from defending yourself you know and
then you transcend naivety and cowardice
and then you become dangerous but maybe
you can transcend dangerous maybe
there's a place past that and well let's
hope there is you say that I'm not sure
if it's in the book but you said it
before that you have to develop some
teeth because you can you shouldn't
mistake weakness for virtue
right and but in Christianity one one
thing that I've struggled with
Christianity is the that the meek shall
inherit them yeah but you know I read
the other cheek yeah other word there
are the worldliness of Christianity that
I find very more grexit yeah not sure if
it's a temperamental no it's a
mistranslation cuz meek look that up
that's a that's a line that always
bothered me and I when I did these
biblical lectures last year which I'm
going to continue by the way as soon as
I can possibly manage it I looked up
that line there's a couple of lines that
really really I couldn't forget them the
poor will always be with us that was one
to those who have everything more shall
be given from those who have everything
from those who have nothing everything
will be taken away that's a rough one
and then the meek shall inherit the
earth but meek is the wrong the word has
slipped over time it isn't what it meant
if you go back into the original if you
go back to the original text let's say
here's a better translation those who
have swords and know how to use them but
keep the machines will inherit the world
okay right that's a little bit different
but that's turning on the cheek
the Christianity yeah well that goes
along without resist not evil but look
look I can tell you some some things
I've learned about that too
so I'll give you a two example so you
know there's been a lot of points for me
in the last 18 months where things could
have gone badly wrong so for example I
went to McMaster University about a year
ago or there abouts and there was a big
demonstration and it was quite obnoxious
I mean there was about 200 people there
that were to see me to came to see me in
about 50 protesters likely and they
drowned me out completely and and and
there was a handful of them who were
really I would say really not good
people like most of them were just
foolish kids and foolish self-righteous
kids who were deluded by their idiot
professors and by their own resentment
but there were four or five people there
who would have been perfectly happy in
that crowd that you described that
descended into Iraq and I can tell who
they were by looking at them they you
know they were people that that just
they just I perhaps I'm wrong but I I
believe that I could see what they were
and there were two of them behind me
woman and a man the woman wasn't quite
so bad but the man was pretty bad and
they were blaring air horns at me an air
horn at me I'm close enough to damage my
hearing which I was not the least bit
impressed about and I told them I said
look you can blow your damn air horn but
if you get it too close to me well I
went I went and had a word with the
police at that point but you know so so
it was quite it was quite provoking and
and and pushy and but I just I knew that
most of it was foolishness and I mostly
watched and I tried to give my talk and
it was completely drown out and then we
had to leave and I gave the rest of my
talk outside but you know all of that
was filmed and then it was put up on
YouTube and all of the consequence of
that holding my temper all of the
consequence of that was positive and
that's one thing I've really learned and
it is associate
with this idea resist not evil and also
of turning the other cheek it's it's not
like you can't respond it's that you
don't and then with that Kathy Newman
interview you know it's the same thing
it's a good really good example of that
is that ain't no one maybe I managed it
because I have had quite a bit of
experience now dealing with hostile
people and hostile press let's say but I
I was able fortunately to stay detached
and and
with with maybe with even with a bit of
a sense of humor during the interview
and not take it personally and not get
offended by it even though what was
happening was deeply wrong there was an
element of being able to be detached
about it and that worked you know like I
didn't really fight with her I didn't
allow her to set the linguistic agenda
let's say but I didn't defend myself any
more than was absolutely necessary you
know it's minimal necessary for
something like that and that was
overwhelmingly it was overwhelmingly
well-received yes I think it was really
I think the detachment sometimes is when
you're in a public situation it's sort
of it's different it's different when
you if you meet someone in streets if
you're one-on-one and they say stuff to
you or if you're at a dinner in a
personal setting or something but when
you're in a public setting you it's
basically a you're on a scene so you can
you can be detached because it's not
really the whole you that disparity says
it's the avatar of yourself or so to
speak or a role you and you inhabit so
you can have you can have patience not
not you you but but I mean as a person
you don't have to take it so personal I
think people make that mistake and I
think personal
yeah well that's that's the thing too is
like it's not easy to
when you should take something
personally and when you shouldn't like I
didn't give you a good example of that
too from politics like years ago who was
running for I think it was Mondale I
think so I might have this wrong but he
was he was governor of Massachusetts now
who was that who ran for governor of
Massachusetts Oh anyways it wasn't
Mondale I don't believe but it doesn't
matter he was governor of Massachusetts
and he had released a prisoner or his
play or his prison system and released a
prisoner who immediately raped someone
and he was being raked over the coals on
a TV show about about the fact that this
has happened I think the rapists name
was Willie Horton if I remember
correctly
Dukakis it was it was Dukakis when
Dukakis was running for president and a
journalist asked him well how would you
feel if Willie Horton had raped your
wife or your daughter and Dukakis gave a
very I would say Placid answer and it it
was one of the things that ensured he
was not going to be elected president
president and what he should have said
was my imagination would immediately go
to the darkest possible place but
because I'm a civilized person and
understand that that pathway leads to
nothing but mayhem I'd be willing to let
the legal system take that moral
obligation from my shoulders because
otherwise everything gets worse that's
the right response the first response is
mess with my family at your peril and
the second response is yeah but I don't
get to start a feud I don't get to
destabilize the entire society in my
pursuit of what you might regard as
justifiable revenge right and so that's
part of that idea of having a sword but
keeping it sheathed
right and it is the opposite of of and I
talked about that in rule
eleven don't bother children with an ax
skateboarding which is in part I suppose
a bit of a diatribe against the idea
that the way that you make men good is
by making them wheat yeah it's a really
uninformed and and naive uninformed and
malicious idea all of those things at
the same time you you make men good by
making them unbelievably strong and
dangerous and then asking them politely
to hold themselves in abeyance at all
times and also I think dangerous is just
an effect of being strong I mean it's
not something if you are strong then you
have the capacity to be dangerous right
it's not something separate from being
strong so all right well it's people are
misinterpreted sometimes when they heard
you that they think you are calling for
sort of the British hyper-masculine kind
of men but that's not what what I've
heard you say whatever you say is that
if you have somebody whose confidence
and you're strong your convictions and
you speak the truth and you're not
afraid to to protest when something is
wrong and stand up for yourself and
stand up for people are we killing need
your protection
then you're strong and then you can be
dangerous but yes and being strong
they've heard that your justice tutorial
so it's the strong have it you're
starting a testosterone count for
something I'm not sure
right right right well of course that's
exactly for people who are afraid of
people for people who are afraid of or
hate competence like to confuse it with
tyranny yeah and you know that I mean
Joe Rogan's kind of an interesting
example in that regard because and so is
this there's a guy named Jack a will Inc
who's got an increasingly popular
podcast in willing cos a he's
guy you know he's very physically
intimidating and I would say
psychologically intimidated by comic
book character ya know he looks and what
he has done in real life well right
exactly exactly yeah well there's also
that that's exactly right he's
articulate and all of those things and
you know and he told me quite clearly
that he could have easily been like a
hyper delinquent when he was a kid but
decided that he was because he's you
know he's he's he's an aggressive guy
and he decided he was going to be a good
person instead and you you can't be a
good person without the capacity for
malevolence interestingly enough and you
know maybe that's one of the reasons if
you think about it metaphysically let's
say I mean one question is always be
well white why is there evil in the
world and I mean this is only a partial
answer but it's possible that you cannot
fully develop your capacity for good
without also developing your capacity
for evil because you have to be able to
do things even if you won't do them I
mean even if it's a matter of learning
how to withstand temptation and until
you're in a position where that
temptation is real you're not
withstanding anything hmm
so you know if you're not sleeping with
a hundred women a year because they're
not lining up to sleep with you that
doesn't make you moral it just makes you
undesirable yeah yeah probably this is
perhaps one of the reasons that bad guys
or so or so they people want to be the
bad guy and they define bad guys
interesting in movies and yes and in
series TV series and and also this is
part of the actually a part of
Christianity which I think is very
interesting is that the prodigal the
Sheep returning to the curb and the
prodigal son and and you find that in
like the most awful criminal who's
starting to have doubts well that's it
one of the best characters in movies I
mean the the awful villain who's having
second thoughts and then in the end
turns out to have a heart of gold yes
yes yes but if you if you are the lamb
that's much more that's a boring movie
like like the lamb who's who's never
done anything wrong can't you can't
because you can't yeah yeah well there's
an interesting there's an interesting
scene in Revelation
so in Revelation which is a very strange
book it's like a hallucinate it's like a
hallucinogenic trip in fact I think it
probably is a hallucinogenic trip
that's my suspicions so Christ comes
back with a sword in his mouth and he
judges humanity and so he's very
merciful in the Gospels but in
Revelation he's the ultimate judge and
the reason for that is that any ideal is
a judge right if you hold something up
as an ideal then you're reflected poorly
in the mirror of that ideal so it's
instantly a judge and there are far more
damned than saved in in in the
Revelation story but Christ tells people
when he judges them I'm it's I'm
paraphrasing but but but the meaning is
is is appropriate if you're hot that's
okay
that's that's commendable if you're cold
that's okay but if you're lukewarm then
I'll vomit you out of my mouth that's
the line and that's so interesting
because it's it's again it's an echo of
what you just described it's like there
there's no virtue in in non-commitment
right there's no virtue in weak
harmlessness in fact and you see that
too I mean when when Hannah Arendt wrote
wrote her her book on Eichmann and in
Jerusalem it's like men in Jerusalem I
believe the banality of evil she talked
about Eichmann and Eichmann was one of
these characters who was a lamb right he
he he was he wasn't your spectacular
cartoon book villain he was the heart
this kind of soft guy next door who sort
of went along to get along and he
happened to be in a hierarchy where the
goal was to eradicate the Jews but who
is he to question the hierarchy hmm
no and so she titled her book the
banality of evil and I always thought
she had the title backwards it should
have been the evil of banality that's a
I haven't thought of that that's yeah
that's a deep thought I just I read a
couple of Christian critiques of your of
your your thoughts and your your book
and one of the one of the critiques was
that you you think that because people
have within the grasp to do good and
evil by themselves you are committing to
a Christian heresy called Pelagianism
yeah yeah see I don't really believe
that yeah I don't really believe that I
mean but it's very difficult because the
Houston orthodoxy then you you can only
do good because of our sinful nature you
can only do good by the grace of God so
we are if we have if we are not sinful
in our nature
if we deny that then you basically
having made committing vanity because we
claim we are so strong like us right so
that that's a claim that I've steam
getting from another actually a critique
that I was thought that I would like to
hear your response it was no critique
yeah but it's it's an unbelievably deep
problem so the first thing I would say
you can only speak metaphorically about
such things in some sense so I would say
the Christian claim is that Christ's
sacrifice redeemed us and so I would say
that's true but we still have to do the
work
you might say well how can both of those
things be the case simultaneously and
the answer is well it depends on your
view of time so and I can't explain it
any deeper than that so I'm not going to
because it would take forever but I
would also say I do believe that you
should step forward to do good humbly I
do believe that if you're going to step
forward to do good that you should do it
well guided by the by the divine images
I do I do believe that you're likely to
err in your judgment of what's good
which is why I entitled the chapter
don't tell the truth or at least don't
lie it isn't obvious to me that you can
discern the truth but it is obvious to
me that sometimes you know when you're
lying yeah and you could stop doing that
and so I think that those critiques are
now but then I would also invert the
criticism and I would say that part of
the danger of modern Western
Christianity in particular I don't think
this is quite the same with the Orthodox
Christian types is that by assuming that
everything good is done by the grace of
God you reduce the burden of the
imitation of Christ the question is what
does it mean to believe in Christ let's
say and one answer to that would be to
say I regard the statement that Christ's
crucifixion redeemed me I regard that
statement as true say I'm a Christian
okay well that's one definition here's
another definition pick up your cross
and walk up the goddamn hill and that's
the proper definition as far as I'm
concerned and so and this is a Nietzsche
and critic criticism of
institutionalized Christianity which is
that it lifts it made the moral burden
to light because the burden is supposed
to be confront evil constrained in your
own heart except the tragedy of being
pick up the load of mortality and walk
uphill it's like god that's rough man
so and then young wrote about that you
know because he was interested in the
Nietzsche and critique and he said look
you got to understand that you can be
cynical about the Catholics and their
idea that you've been redeemed by an
external source say it's not that it's
not precisely that clear will parody a
bit for the sake of argument and maybe
you can also be cynical about the idea
that you can go in and confess and
receive absolution and walk out sin free
but what you have to understand is the
church is somewhat merciful in its
endeavors because it's trying to also
free people from the intolerable
consciousness of their own insufficiency
you know cuz I could say to you well you
need to bear the weight of all your
transgressions it's like Jesus really
with no mercy that's how we're going to
play this who could tolerate that and
the Catholics at least say well look
you're fallible you're gonna make all
sorts of mistakes it's gonna happen over
and over at least and go in and have the
burden lifted from you time to time
you're supposed to play it straight
you're supposed to go in and actually
confess and repent and and try to do
better in the future
but at least you don't have to drag your
catastrophic cell past itself along with
you every step of the way
so anyways I'm not trying to elevate
human beings to the status of demigods
you know but I guess I am suggesting
that we could at least participate in
that to the degree that we're willing to
hoist our own burdens and I do think we
should do that with humility and without
thinking that we can see the way forward
so clearly I do think we can walk away
from Auschwitz though yeah I think so
too
I would also I know this was this has
been a recurring question for you and
I'm not sure if I asked me the last time
really but it's about truth and how you
return to that Christian
some parts of Christianity at least has
been true you said like that the truth
for the individual I think you said and
how my question is how can
how can this be true and and for 4cs
lewis when he when he's not like accept
that that christianity was true for him
it was like a mixture he was talked into
it by talking and I don't remember that
a guy's name
but another friend and he said I think
the combination of the myth of a dying
God he always loved the dying gods like
Dionysus under and Paul Durand but but
but in Christ it can be combining that
the dying God motif and the myth with an
actual historical figure yeah he
actually said that this is a it's not
just a myth it's a true belief it's me
because it's also historical and then he
said that and I mean distinguished like
if you if you watch from the outside and
analyze it well of course you can see
that it's it's just you can see the
similarities and as a scientist but from
the inside you can see the truth so that
was his view of it yeah well here's a
here's a strange possibility like one of
the things that's happened to me as I've
delved farther and farther into
religious stories is that I've found
continually that their depth is
inexhaustible and at some point it
becomes less impossible that they're
true then it is impossible that they're
not true something like that now okay
now I'm not so there there there are
there are truths in Genesis that are
unfathomably deep now and I've outlined
them to the best of my ability in the
biblical series that I did now I don't
know how to reconcile those truths with
with with cyant with the scientific view
of the world that the the view the the
fact that the universe is fourteen
billion years old and that we've crawled
our way up from the sludge in the mud I
don't know how those things coexist
precisely I know that there are
routes that guide behavior and there are
truths that describe the material world
but I certainly don't think that the
truths that we have that describe the
material world are final truths because
I don't think our materialist viewpoint
is accurate it's accurate for some
purposes obviously and I am a practicing
scientist and an informed one I would
say I don't believe that people act as
if they confront a material reality I
believe that people act as if they
confront an infinite realm of
possibility one pole of which is heaven
and the other pole of which is hell and
I believe that we treat each other as if
that's the world that we live in because
we upbraid each other for not upholding
our moral duty and we understand what
that means and we upgrade ourselves for
being less than we could and so we
confront a world of potential and we
don't have a good model for that and the
mythological descriptions describe the
human being as the eternal confronter of
a world of potential and there's
something about that that's accurate now
with regards to this Christian story
specifically I do think the idea that
that eternal myth was made historically
concrete is one of the things about
Christianity that's unutterably powerful
I don't know what the limits are but
let's say that what you're called upon
to do until in life is to open yourself
up to the tragedy of being completely to
to accept it to welcome it even even to
love it if you can do that and that's no
easy thing you watched Iraq being
invaded there's no easy way of loving
now there's no easy way of saying yes to
that but your job in some sense as a as
a incarnated finite creature is to say
yes to the possibilities of being in
every possible way the question is well
what's the upper limit to that like what
are the transformations that are
possible as a consequence of doing that
and the answer to that is we don't know
the Christian story is in part an
investigation of that so if you're
willing to accept your if you're willing
to accept the brutality of the mob the
betrayal of your friends the torch
of your existence and your unjust death
if you're willing to accept that and
welcome it what happens to you and the
answer is try it and find out I think
I'm gonna pass on just that yeah you
know when you when you were when you
decided to immerse yourself in what was
happening in Iraq you know you could
have looked away
yeah and for I often find that my my
role as a journalist or I'm not a real
journalist I'm more like in that it's
I'm an editorial writer but it's sort of
a mist between me and some reality so I
could I can I can do it as a take on my
my jackets and then I watch the reality
through that lens so so it sort of
shields me from from from some some of
it yeah well that's the advantage having
a well-developed persona from the Union
perspective you know you put on an image
like like Clark Kent
like Superman puts on Clark Kent that's
why superheroes always have an enormity
of alter ego right they have to be able
to live in the normal world right so you
need to have an element of yourself that
can that can exist
that can act as a mask between you and
the world I suppose that's what a
persona is so but I mean to the degree
that you're able to open your eyes you
know [ __ ] Nietzsche also said you could
determine the depth of a man's character
by observing how much truth he's willing
to tolerate mm-hmm right right which is
you know you think well how can that be
associated with the idea of the truth
will set you free it's like well it
might set you free but it will take you
places you're not sure you want to go
first yeah sort of cliche in the movie
matrix when neo wakes up and he's
flushed down like a drainpipe and then
they woken up into this awful awful
world and that's reality
that's the truth that's the underworld
you have this but it's an awful truth
this that's really bleak but hopefully
the truth is not that bleak all the time
yeah well you know there's an old well
the funny thing is there's an old
Christian idea too that when Christ was
crucified he went and Herald hell before
he rose to heaven it's like there is
this idea that you don't go up without
going down and I really do believe
that's true and I think that maybe see
one of the images in Genesis that's
really hard to understand is that when
God throws Adam and Eve out of paradise
he puts an angel at the gates of
paradise with with flaming swords to bar
the way you might think well why would
God bar the way to paradise with with
flaming swords and maybe the flaming
swords cut all the dead wood off before
you step through the gate and if you're
all Deadwood then there's nothing left
of you once the flaming swords are done
with you and to observe what you observe
with the Iraq invasion that's a set of
flaming swords you know because what
you're watching is what human beings are
like and you happen to be one and to the
degree that you're like that that's you
doing that that's a hell of a thing -
that's a hell of a thing to realize you
think well what's the right response to
watching that and I would say to stop
being an evil person
and that's no simple thing one of the
things with these people that goes there
and joins the Islamic state is that they
are not all evil
they are just none of them are evil of
course and they're Psychopaths and they
are and I mean if you are a psychopath
they really want to do violence and
that's a great place to be and you can
probably do great there but there are
also people joining there are they are
really they want to do good they just
really shouldn't have a really twisted
sense of what's good and that's one of
the most depressing things about Islamic
state is that some of the people that
goes there they do horrible things and
then they regret themselves but I mean
how could you let them back into society
after what they've done yeah well how
can they let themselves back yeah so so
we say the power of ideas is that you
can you can convert people that under
other circumstances would have done good
or evil instead well this is partly why
I tried in some sense or I allowed in
some sense 12 rules and my lectures as
well to be so harsh because imagine that
there are many young men who are looking
for an adventure they need an adventure
right they need an adventure and maybe
their normative life is sufficiently
soft and undemanding so that they could
recede into a kind of domestic
unconsciousness as an alternative but
there's nothing in that except a
prolonged prolonged non-existence
self-contempt and bitterness right it's
not good you need to be called to an
adventure and so I would say well look
and this is what ideologies offer young
people is the call to an adventure but
it's a false adventure I would say
instead look you want an adventurers
open up your eyes open up your eyes to
what the world is really like and then
take your place in it as a productive
awake attentive and truthful being and
how far you can walk uphill that's an
adventure
it's the alternative to the call to war
right because the call to war is an
adventure William James said 130 hundred
and forty years ago we need a moral
equivalent to war hmm and and it touches
on exactly what you're saying is these
these kids who are lost let's say and
maybe somewhat bitter and resentful as a
consequence they see in Isis a call to
adventure well you know I understand
that I saw this kid once in Montreal and
an outside shopping mall he was about
six foot five and he was dressed up like
a punk rocker you know and he was
standing on the corner with two pink
shopping bags in his hand and I thought
what a ridiculous figure he cut because
he was all dressed up like a Viking
right he was ready to go out there and
have his damn adventure and what he was
doing instead was standing in an outdoor
shopping mall with two pink shopping
bags it's like come up to a kid like
that and you say hey you want to go get
into some trouble some interesting
trouble he's gonna like throw those
shopping bags away and come with you
instantly it's like okay well you need
some interesting trouble well what could
that be well here's something get your
act together discipline yourself look at
the world see if you can find a problem
to solve grow up you know when what's so
interesting or one of the things that's
been so interesting to me to observe as
a consequence of what I've been talking
about is just how many people are
starving for that message yeah you know
I have after my talks now say I was in
LA and about 700 people lined up
afterwards to have a book signed and
they all the vast majority of them have
a story to tell and so the little
exchanges I have with people are very
intense you know because they want to
have a minute to tell me what's
happening and or thirty Seconds even and
they say look here was ten things going
terribly wrong with my life and I've
been trying to aim up and say what I
have to say it everything's much better
thank you very much and I think God good
work and then the next person comes up
and says the same thing and I've got
like 25,000 letters that have said that
since August and so you know there is a
way of calling people to an adventure
that perhaps isn't destructive they have
enough right in front of them to have a
great adventure if they're if they're
willing let's say to try not to lie and
to tell the truth and to aim uphill
maybe that adventures right in front of
us maybe that's part of maybe that's
part of the process of engendering
paradise to find the adventure in in to
find the proper divide don't excuse me
to find the divine adventure in every
individual life that's the that's that
union of the divine and the historical
in Christianity - right it's to make the
archetype real yeah I think we'll so the
rule number six set your house in
perfect order before you criticize the
world I think that's also you begin you
begin with yourself and you you start to
be be the change so to speak and that's
a way out of being bitter against the
world to at least not to begin with at
least it's just that's right it's a
start you can say to yourself look
everything looks pretty terrible to me
what the hell how can it be this way but
then you can take the next step and say
yeah maybe I'm not everything I could be
so how about if I try to be everything I
could be and then think about it again
later yeah and that's the right that's
because the alternative to that is just
a catastrophe right yeah and I think
that's that's the key to dignity really
right you you can be dignified even if
you're you're not the best
you're not strong if you're not the most
beautiful but if you if you set yourself
in order and you take yourself seriously
then you can have dignity and other
other people notice it and you will
notice it yes
great that's a great place to start from
and to strive for really that's one of
the most one of the best
things about your book really that you
bring dignity into I think you bring
dignity into people's lives with this
book on with your lectures but that's
what one of the takeaways I had from
speaking with people because at after
the last interview why I did and then
people read the piece say I wrote and
then people a lot of people thank me for
introducing you to them in Sweden and
and then that's been one of the
recurring themes like that but the thing
feels so much stronger themselves I
think that's a great that's a great
observation I mean you know our society
is weak because we think about happiness
why don't we think about dignity why
don't we think about nobility why don't
we think about truth and responsibility
or beauty all of those things they're
they're much they're the values that
sustain you through suffering happiness
cannot do that not that happiness is to
be to be what there's no there's no
utility and contempt for happiness thank
God if it comes
but dignity I mean we can't even when is
the last time you heard someone talk
about that part of the public discourse
and it's so crucial I think also
happiness is more of a byproduct than an
improvement
it's not something you if you strive for
it too much you won't get it do you mean
your dignity your happiness happiness
yes definitely well you might say if you
strive for dignity and truth sometimes
you'll be rewarded with happiness Yeah
right
that's a grace of God that the happiness
that's not something you can conjure up
on your own good luck trying yeah so I
think I've taken up almost two hours of
your time and will write the piece about
your book and I will have a mix thing to
be with you and also just
I was writing this piece immobile
it was 18,000 characters and I was just
so stressed out and I was telling my
wife right it's like fighting in
hydrates like new heads coming up all
the time and she was just laughing at me
like oh you you read too much you know
fearsome how he says he's invaded your
language cheater
yes that's oh that's well that's a
terrible thing with regards to
archetypal stories is that once you hear
them there's no getting rid of them but
my wife has also read your books away to
where we've talked a lot about you or
say hello to her for me and maybe we can
bump into each other when I come to
Sweden yeah you should really come
coming in the fall I would love to meet
but then I'll stay in touch with with
regards to the when I'm done with the
text and everything and great nice
talking with you
nice talking to you Kate bye-bye